A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - General Court Records, 1781-1862
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - General Court Records, 1781-1862
The Library of Virginia
APA 96
9.45 cu. ft. (21 boxes)
Virginia. Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
The General Court operated during the colonial period as the principal court and the only court of final appeal in Virginia. It was composed of the members of the governor's council. Its operation was suspended during the first year of the revolutionary war, but was reestablished by an act of the General Assembly passed at its session begun in October 1777.
The jurisdiction of the new General Court was reduced substantially from that of its colonial predecessor. Besides hearing appeals on criminal cases the court was concerned with common law cases involving debtors, the probate of wills and granting of administrations, and, until 1814, the recording of deeds. Most civil cases were heard by the Supreme Court of Appeals.
The General Court was composed of judges of other state courts who met at the state capitol. The constitution adopted in 1851 abolished the General Court, and the cases still pending before it were transferred to the Supreme Court of Appeals. Almost all of the records of the General Court were destroyed in the Richmond evacuation fire of 3 April 1865.
During its session begun in November 1781 the General Assembly passed an act authorizing the solicitor general to file motions in the General Court against local officials who were delinquent in their accounts with the commonwealth. Each official was notified that a motion was pending so he could settle his accounts before the case was heard. Failing this, the court entered a judgment against the official, and the solicitor issued a request that the judgment be executed. After the judgment was executed, the fact was noted in a return made to the court. These functions devolved upon the auditor of public accounts after the solicitor general was abolished in 1792.
Scope and Content
Records, 1786-1862, including accounts, correspondence, executions, judgments, motions, receipts, and returns of the Virginia General Court. The collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title into twenty-one boxes.
The Solicitor General (pre-1792) and Auditor of Public Accounts (post-1792) were authorized by the General Assembly to file motions in the General Court against local officials who were delinquent in their accounts with the Commonwealth. The delinquent accounts included fines (militia fines, taxes, proceeds for sale of land, etc.) collected by local officials (sheriffs, county clerks, etc.) but not paid to the Commonwealth. The process included notifying the local official that a motion was pending (notices and correspondence) so that he could settle his accounts before the case was heard. Failing this the court entered a judgment (judgments) against the official and the solicitor issued a request that the judgment be executed (executions and receipts for executions). After the judgment was executed the fact was noted in a return made to the court (returns).
Of note are Solicitor's Office Correspondence and Directions, 1784-1791, from Leighton Wood, Jr., Solicitor General, to agents, delivering notices of taxes due of various county clerks and sheriffs. The correspondence lists the localities to visit and to whom to provide the notices. Also included are notes on expenses accrued by agents on their trips. Also included are judgments containing lists of judgements due and notices from the Auditor's Office sent to county clerks and sheriffs stating the amount owed and for what reason. Also included are lists of motions before the General Court.
These records are part of Auditor of Public Accounts. Office Records: State Courts - General Court.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Allen, John J. [Agent for Harrison and Lewis Counties], Correspondence, 1821-1825 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Allen, John J. [Agent for Harrison and Lewis Counties], Correspondence, 1826-1828 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Chapin, Phineas [Agent for Harrison and Lewis Counties], Correspondence, 1829-1831 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1783 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1784 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1785 August-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1786 March-July (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1786 August (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1787 May-1788 November (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1789 March-May (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1789 September (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1789 October (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence and Directions, Solicitor's Office, 1790-1793 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Executions, List, 1790 (Box 3 [oversize], Folder 1)
- Executions, List, 1791-1792 (Box 3 [oversize], Folder 2)
- Execution Books [Nos. 4 & 5], 1791-1792 (Box 3 [oversize], Folder 3)
- Executions, List, 1793-1794 (Box 3 [oversize], Folder 4)
- Executions, List, 1794-1795 (Box 3 [oversize], Folder 5)
- Executions, List, 1795-1796 (Box 3 [oversize], Folder 6)
- Executions, List, 1810-1814 (Box 3 [oversize], Folder 7)
- Executions, Correspondence, 1786-1851 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Executions, Against Sheriffs, 1783-1787 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Executions, Against Sheriffs, 1788-1817 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Judgments, Accounts for payments, 1787-1814 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Judgement, 1782-1788 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Judgement, Statement Book No. 2, 1782-1786 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Judgement, Statement Book No. 4, 1782-1790 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Judgement, Statement Book No. 5, 1785-1789 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Judgement, Statement Book No. 6, 1783-1792 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 7, 1784-1793 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 9, 1783-1793 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 10, 1784-1795 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 11, 1784-1795 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 12, 1783-1794 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 13, 1783-1798 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 16-19, 1784-1798 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 20-21, 1792-1799 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 24-32, 1784-1803 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 33-45, 1785-1811 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. 46-57, 1811-1821 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. [unknown], 1817-1821 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Judgments, Statement Book No. [unknown], 1820-1823 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Judgments, 1790-1794 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Judgments, 1795-1799 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Judgments, 1800-1804 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Judgments, 1805-1806 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Judgments, 1807-1813 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Judgments, 1814-1820 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Judgments, 1852 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
- Judgments, 1855 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Judgments, 1857 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
- Judgments, 1858 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
- Judgments, Chronological, 1790-1795 (Box 8 [oversize])
- Judgments, By county, 1790-1844 (Box 8 [oversize])
- Judgments, 1800-1820 (Box 8 [oversize])
- Lists of motions and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1781-1783 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Lists of motions and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1783-1784 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Lists of motions and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1784-1785 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1785 October (Box 7, Folder 8)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1785 December (Box 9, Folder 1)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1786 April (Box 9, Folder 2)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1786 October (Box 9, Folder 3)
- List of motions, General Court, 1787 January-April (Box 9, Folder 4)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1788 June (Box 9, Folder 5)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1788 October (Box 9, Folder 6)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1788 December (Box 9, Folder 7)
- List of motions, General Court, 1789 June (Box 9, Folder 8)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1789 June (Box 9, Folder 9)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1789 November (Box 9, Folder 10)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1790 June (Box 9, Folder 11)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1790 November (Box 9, Folder 12)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1791 June (Box 9, Folder 13)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1791 November (Box 9, Folder 14)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1792 June (Box 10, Folder 1)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1792 November (Box 10, Folder 2)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1793 June (Box 10, Folder 3)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1793 November (Box 10, Folder 4)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1794 June (Box 10, Folder 5)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1794 November (Box 10, Folder 6)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1795 June (Box 10, Folder 7)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1795 November (Box 10, Folder 8)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1797 June (Box 10, Folder 9)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1797 November-1800 June (Box 10, Folder 10)
- List of motions, General Court [volume], 1800 November-1814 June (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Memoranda of costs of suit received by J.E. Heath, 1820 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1783 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1784 February-March (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, Counties A-G, 1784 September-October (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, Counties H-Y, 1784 September-October (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, Counties A-H, 1785 March (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, Counties J-Y, 1785 March (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1785 April (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, Counties A-G, 1785 August (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, Counties H-L, 1785 August (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, Counties M-Y, 1785 August (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1786 February-April (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1786 August-December (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1787 February (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1787 March (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1787 May (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1788 November (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
- Notices and correspondence, Solicitor's Office, 1789-1791 (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1792-1794 (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1793-1802 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1807-1814 (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1815 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1815-1819 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1817-1821 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1820-1822 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1822-1824 (Box 13, Folder 6)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1826-1827 (Box 13, Folder 7)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1834-1847 (Box 13, Folder 8)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1847 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1849-1851 (Box 13, Folder 11)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1851 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1853-1854 (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1855 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1856 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1858-1859 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Notices and correspondence, Auditor's Office, 1860-1861 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Notices and correspondence, Notary Public, Auditor's Office, 1852-1862 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Peter T. Phillips [John Trent, James B. Anderson, Miller Woodson, Watkins Johnson, and Leonard Bosher] bond, 1827 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1785, 1789 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1789 March-September (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1790 April-May (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1790 July-November (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1791 March-April (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1791 August-September (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1792 June-July (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1792 August (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1793 February-March (Box 15, Folder 7)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1793 June-August (Box 15, Folder 8)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1793 September-October (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1794 January-March (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1794 April (Box 15, Folder 11)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1794 May (Box 15, Folder 12)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1794 June-August (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1794 September (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1794 October (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1795 February (Box 16, Folder 4)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1795 March (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1795 April (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1795 May-October, December (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1796 February (Box 16, Folder 8)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1796 March-April (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1796 June-October (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1797 February-May (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1797 July (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1797 August-November (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1798 March-May (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1798 July-September (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1799 February-April (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1799 July-December (Box 17, Folder 5)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1800 January-March (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1800 April-May (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1800 July (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1800 August-October (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1801 February-March (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1801 March-May (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1801 July (Box 18, Folder 4-5)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1801 August-December (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1802 January-February (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1802 March-May (Box 18, Folder 8)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1802 June-July (Box 18, Folder 9)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1802 August-October (Box 18, Folder 10)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1803 January-December (Box 18, Folder 10)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1804 January-April (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1804 July-August (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1805 February-April (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1805 June-October (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1806 February (Box 19, Folder 5)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1806 March-April (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1806 July-October (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1807 February-April (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1807 July (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1807 August-October (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1808 February-March (Box 19, Folder 11)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1808 April (Box 19, Folder 12)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1808 July-November (Box 19, Folder 13)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1809 February-April (Box 20, Folder 1)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1809 June-November (Box 20, Folder 2)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1810 January-March (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1810 April-May (Box 20, Folder 4)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1810 July-September (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1811 March-May (Box 20, Folder 6)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1811 June-August (Box 20, Folder 7)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1812 March-April (Box 20, Folder 8)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1812 June-August (Box 20, Folder 9)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1813 March-November (Box 20, Folder 10)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1814 February-April (Box 20, Folder 11)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1814 July-September (Box 20, Folder 12)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1815 July-September (Box 20, Folder 13)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1816 April-August (Box 20, Folder 14)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1817 July-October (Box 20, Folder 15)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1818 March-May (Box 20, Folder 16)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1818 August-November (Box 20, Folder 17)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1824 July-December (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1825 January-October (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1826 April-October (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1827 April-September (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1828 April-August (Box 21, Folder 5)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1829 March-August (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1830 February-September (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Receipts for executions returnable to the General Court, 1831, 1833-1837 (Box 21, Folder 8)
- Returns on executions issued by the General Court, 1781-1784 (Box 21, Folder 9)
- Returns on executions issued by the General Court, 1785-1786 (Box 21, Folder 10)
- Returns on executions issued by the General Court, 1786-1787 (Box 21, Folder 11)
- Returns on executions issued by the General Court, 1788-1790 (Box 21, Folder 12)
- Capt. Francis Smith vs. the Commonwealth, 1783-1785 (Box 21, Folder 13)